Now, extinction is a different kind of death.
حاليا أصبح الانقراض نوع مختلفمن الموت.
It's bigger.
إنه أكبر.
We didn't really realize that until 1914,
لم نتفطن لذلك إلا في 1914
when the last passenger pigeon, a female named Martha,
عندما ماتت آخر حمامة مهاجرةاسمها مارثا
died at the Cincinnati zoo.
بحديقة سينسيناتي للحيوانات.
This had been the most abundant bird in the world
كانت ولسنوات أكثر الطيورتعداد بالعالم
that'd been in North America for six million years.
عاشت بشمال أمريكا ل 6 ملايين سنة.
Suddenly it wasn't here at all.
لتختفي فجأة بالكامل.
Flocks that were a mile wide and 400 miles long
اسراب بلغ عرضها 1,5 كلموطولها 600 كلم
used to darken the sun.
كانت تغطي الشمس.
Aldo Leopold said this was a biological storm,
كان ألدو ليوبولد يصفها بأنهاكانت كعاصفة بيولوجية
a feathered tempest.
أو كعاصفة من الريش.
And indeed it was a keystone species
وكان حقا طيرا جد مهم
that enriched the entire eastern deciduous forest,
أثرى كل الغابة المتأكلة بالغرب
from the Mississippi to the Atlantic,
من المسيسيبي حتى المحيط الأطلسي
from Canada down to the Gulf.
ومن كندا نزولا حتى الخليج.
But it went from five billion birds to zero in just a couple decades.
لكن أعدادها انخفضت من 5 مليارات طيرإلى 0 في بضعة عقود فقط.
What happened?
ما الذي وقع؟
Well, commercial hunting happened.
الذي حدث هو ظهورالصيد التجاري.
These birds were hunted for meat that was sold by the ton,
صيدت تلك الطيور من أجل لحومهاالتي بيعت بالأطنان
and it was easy to do because when those big flocks
وكان اصطيادها سهلالأنه عندما كان السرب الضخم
came down to the ground, they were so dense
يحط على الأرض بأعداده الكبيرة
that hundreds of hunters and netters could show up
كان من السهل على مئات الصيادينوناصبي الأفخاخ
and slaughter them by the tens of thousands.
أن يذبحوها بعشرات الآلاف.
It was the cheapest source of protein in America.
كان أرخس مصدر للبروتين بأمريكا.
By the end of the century, there was nothing left
وفي نهاية القرن لمي بتبقى منها شيء
but these beautiful skins in museum specimen drawers.
ماعدا هذه الجلود الجميلةبأدراج متحف التاريخ الطبيعي.
There's an upside to the story.
رغم ذلك فإن لهذه القصة جانب جيد.
This made people realize that the same thing
فقد دفع ذلك الناس لأن يدركواأن نفس الشيء
was about to happen to the American bison,
كان يحدث للبيسون الأمريكي
and so these birds saved the buffalos.
وبشكل ما أنقذت الطيور البيسون.
But a lot of other animals weren't saved.
لكن العديد من الحيوانات لم يتم إنقاذها.
The Carolina parakeet was a parrot that lit up backyards everywhere.
كانت طيور بَرَاكِيت كَارُولَيْنَا تملأخلفيات المنازل في كل مكان.
It was hunted to death for its feathers.
اصطيدت ختى الانقراض من أجل ريشها.
There was a bird that people liked on the East Coast called the heath hen.
كان هناك طائر يدعى بدجاجة هِيثْأحبها سكان الساحل الشرقي
It was loved. They tried to protect it. It died anyway.
كانت محبوبة.وقد حاولوا إنقاضها لكن رغم ذلك انقرضت.
A local newspaper spelled out, "There is no survivor,
وقد كتبت الصحافة المحلية معنونة،"ليس هناك ناج
there is no future, there is no life to be recreated in this form ever again."
ولا آمل ولن نشاهد كائنا مثل هذا بعد الآن."
There's a sense of deep tragedy that goes with these things,
هناك إحساس عميق بالآسىيصاحب هذه الأشياء عند وقوعها
and it happened to lots of birds that people loved.
وقد تعرضت العديد من الطيورالتي أحبها الناس لذلك.
It happened to lots of mammals.
وتعرضت له أيضا الكثير من الثدييات.
Another keystone species is a famous animal
هناك نوع أخر مشهور وجد مهممن الحيونات
called the European aurochs.
يدعى بالأُرْخُص الأوروبي.
There was sort of a movie made about it recently.
وقد أنتج مؤخرا فيلم يتحدث عنه.
And the aurochs was like the bison.
كان الأُرْخُص يشبه البيسون.
This was an animal that basically kept the forest
كان حيوانا يعيش بالغابة
mixed with grasslands across the entire Europe and Asian continent,
والسهول عبر كلٍ من قارتيأوروبا وآسيا
from Spain to Korea.
ومن إسبانيا حتى كوريا.
The documentation of this animal goes back
وتعود المصادر الشاهدة على وجود هذا الحيوان
to the Lascaux cave paintings.
إلى رسومات كهف لاسكو.
The extinctions still go on.
مازالت حالات الانقراض تتزايد.
There's an ibex in Spain called the bucardo.
كتيس الجبل بإسبانيا المسمى بُوكَارْدُو.
It went extinct in 2000.
انقرض عام 2000.
There was a marvelous animal, a marsupial wolf
كان هناك حيوان أخر هو ذئب تَسْمَانْيَا
called the thylacine in Tasmania, south of Australia,
يسمى الثَّيلسين في تسمانيا بجنوب أستراليا
called the Tasmanian tiger.
ويسمى أيضا بنمر تسمانيا.
It was hunted until there were just a few left to die in zoos.
اصطيد ولم يبقى منه سوى عدد قليلللموت بحدائق الحيوانات.
A little bit of film was shot.
صور في هذا الفيلم القصير.
Sorrow, anger, mourning.
آسى وغضب وحزن.
Don't mourn. Organize.
لا تحزنوا بل اتحدوا.
What if you could find out that, using the DNA in museum specimens,
ماذا لو أمكنكم استخدام الحمض النوويالموجود بمتحف التاريخ الطبيعي،
fossils maybe up to 200,000 years old
كالحفريات التي قد يزيد عمرهاعن 200.000 سنة،
could be used to bring species back,
من إعادة تلك الحيونات للحياة،
what would you do? Where would you start?
ما الذي قد تفعلونه؟ من أين ستبدأون؟
Well, you'd start by finding out if the biotech is really there.
يمكنكم البدء بالتأكد من توفرالتقنية اللازمة.
I started with my wife, Ryan Phelan,
فيما يخصنيبدأت مع زوجتي رِيَانْ فِيلاَن،
who ran a biotech business called DNA Direct,
التي تدير شركة تدعى "دي إن أي ديركت"،
and through her, one of her colleagues, George Church,
وبفضلها التقيت أحد زملاءها،جورج تشورش،
one of the leading genetic engineers
واحد من رواد الهندسة الجينية
who turned out to be also obsessed with passenger pigeons
الذي تبين أنه مهووس أيضابالحمام المهاجر
and a lot of confidence
والواثق بشدة أن
that methodologies he was working on
مناهجه التي عمل عليها
might actually do the deed.
ربما ستأتي بنتيجة.
So he and Ryan organized and hosted a meeting
لدى قام هو وريانعلى تنظيم واستضافت اجتماع
at the Wyss Institute in Harvard bringing together
بمعهد ويس بهارفاردوالذي جمع
specialists on passenger pigeons, conservation ornithologists, bioethicists,
متخصصين بالحمام المهاجروعلماء الطيور الانحفاظية وأخلاقيات علم الأحياء
and fortunately passenger pigeon DNA had already been sequenced
ولحسن الحظ فقد تم بالفعلتحديد تسلسل الحمض النووي للحمام المهاجر
by a molecular biologist named Beth Shapiro.
من طرف عالمة الأحياء الجزيئيةبِيثْ شَابِيرُو.
All she needed from those specimens at the Smithsonian
كل ما كانت بحاجة إليه من تلك الطيورالموجودة عند سْمِيثْسُونْيَانْ
was a little bit of toe pad tissue,
كان القليل من نسيج أصبع قدمها،
because down in there is what is called ancient DNA.
ففي ذلك المكان يوجدما يدعى بالحمض النووي القديم.
It's DNA which is pretty badly fragmented,
هو حمض نووي منقسم بشكل سيء،
but with good techniques now, you can basically reassemble the whole genome.
ولكن بفضل التقنيات الحديثةيمكنكم إعادة بناء المَجِين بالكامل.
Then the question is, can you reassemble,
ليبقى السؤال،هل يمكنكم إعادة بناء
with that genome, the whole bird?
الطائر بواسطة هذا المَجِين؟
George Church thinks you can.
يعتقد جورج تشورش أنه بالإمكان ذلك.
So in his book, "Regenesis," which I recommend,
في كتابه "رِجِنِيسِيسْ" الذي أنصح بقراءته
he has a chapter on the science of bringing back extinct species,
يوجد به باب يتحدث حولعلم استعادة الكائنات المنقرضة
and he has a machine called
ولديه آلة تدعى
the Multiplex Automated Genome Engineering machine.
بالآلة المركَّبَة لهندسة الجين.
It's kind of like an evolution machine.
هي كنوع من آلات المستقبل.
You try combinations of genes that you write
بحيث تجربون التركيبات الجينيةالتي تعدونها
at the cell level and then in organs on a chip,
على مستوى الخليةثم على مستوى رقاقات صناعية
and the ones that win, that you can then put
لنتمكن بعدها بوضع تلك التي نجحت
into a living organism. It'll work.
بالكائن الحي. هذا الأمر سينجح.
The precision of this, one of George's famous unreadable slides,
وللعلم، فإن واحدةمن شرائح جورج الشهيرة الغير قابلة للقراءة
nevertheless points out that there's a level of precision here
تشير بشكل ما إلى أن هناك نسبة نجاح
right down to the individual base pair.
نصل لمستوى زوج واحد قاعدي.
The passenger pigeon has 1.3 billion base pairs in its genome.
يملك الحمام المهاجر1.3 مليار زوج قاعدي بجيناته.
So what you're getting is the capability now
إذا فالذي تستطيعون فعله اليوم
of replacing one gene with another variation of that gene.
هو تغيير جين واحد بأخر مختلف.
It's called an allele.
وهذا يسمى بالأَلِيل.
Well that's what happens in normal hybridization anyway.
وهذا ما نقوم بهخلال عملية التهجين العادية
So this is a form of synthetic hybridization of the genome
وهو نوع من التهجين الاصطناعي
of an extinct species
لكائن منقرض
with the genome of its closest living relative.
بواسطة جينات أقرب كائن حي له.
Now along the way, George points out that
أود أن اخبركم أن جورج أشار دائما إلى أن
his technology, the technology of synthetic biology,
تقنيته وهي تكنولوجيا علم الأحياء الصناعية،
is currently accelerating at four times the rate of Moore's Law.
حاليا أسرع 4 مرات من معدل قانون مور.
It's been doing that since 2005, and it's likely to continue.
وقد بدأ العمل عليها منذ 2005ومن المحتمل أن تستمر.
Okay, the closest living relative of the passenger pigeon
أقرب كائن حي للحمام المهاجر
is the band-tailed pigeon. They're abundant. There's some around here.
هو الحمام ذو الذيل المخطط وهو متواجد بكثرةويوجد البعض منها بهذه النواحي.
Genetically, the band-tailed pigeon already is
جينيا الحمام ذو الذيل المخطط هو فعليا
mostly living passenger pigeon.
حمام مهاجر.
There's just some bits that are band-tailed pigeon.
هناك القليل فقط من الأشياءالتي تجعل منه حمامة ذات ذيل مخطط.
If you replace those bits with passenger pigeon bits,
إن أنتم غيرتم تلك الأشياءبأخرى للحمام المهاجر
you've got the extinct bird back, cooing at you.
ستحصلون على طائر منقرض يهدل أمامكم.
Now, there's work to do.
لكن هناك الكثير للقيام به.
You have to figure out exactly what genes matter.
عليكم الحصول على الجينات المناسبة.
So there's genes for the short tail in the band-tailed pigeon,
فالحمام ذو الذيل المخطط مثلالديه جينات للذيل القصير
genes for the long tail in the passenger pigeon,
بينما للحمام المهاجر جينات للذيل الطويل
and so on with the red eye, peach-colored breast, flocking, and so on.
وللعيون الحمراء وللصدر البرتقالي إلخ.
Add them all up and the result won't be perfect.
قد لا تكون نتيجة جمع كل تلك الجينات مثالية
But it should be be perfect enough,
لكنها ستكون مثالية نوع ما
because nature doesn't do perfect either.
فالطبيعة أيضا تخطئ أحيانا.
So this meeting in Boston led to three things.
وقد خلص ذلك الاجتماع في بوسطن إلى 3 أشياء.
First off, Ryan and I decided to create a nonprofit
أولا: قررنا ريان وأنا خلق مشروع غير ربحي
called Revive and Restore that would push de-extinction generally
يدعى "روفايف أند ريستور"الذي سيعالج الإنقراض بشكل عام
and try to have it go in a responsible way,
وسنحاول القيام بذلك بشكل مسؤول
and we would push ahead with the passenger pigeon.
ويمكننا البدء من الحمام المهاجر.
Another direct result was a young grad student named Ben Novak,
ثانيا: طالب حديث التخرج يدعى بِينْ نُوفَاكْ
who had been obsessed with passenger pigeons since he was 14
مهووس بالحمام المهاجر منذ سن 14
and had also learned how to work with ancient DNA,
ودارس أيضا لكيفيةالعمل بالحمض النووي القديم
himself sequenced the passenger pigeon,
وقد قام وحده بتحديدتسلسل الحمض النووي للحمام المهاجر
using money from his family and friends.
باستخدام أموال الأسرته والأصدقاء.
We hired him full-time.
وقد قمنا بتوظيفه بدوام كامل.
Now, this photograph I took of him last year at the Smithsonian,
هذه صورة التقطتها له السنة الماضيةبسميثسونيان
he's looking down at Martha,
إنه ينظر إلى مارثا
the last passenger pigeon alive.
أخر حمامة مهاجرة على قيد الحياة.
So if he's successful, she won't be the last.
إن هو نجح فلن تكون الأخيرة.
The third result of the Boston meeting was the realization
ثالثا: كان الإدراك
that there are scientists all over the world
بأن هناك علماء حول العالم
working on various forms of de-extinction,
يعملون على أنواع متعددةمن الحيوانات لاستعادتها من الانقراض،
but they'd never met each other.
لكنهم لم يجتمعوا من قبل.
And National Geographic got interested
وقد اهتمت ناشونال جيوغرافيك بهم
because National Geographic has the theory that
لأن لدى ناشونال جيوغرافيك نظرية بأنه
the last century, discovery was basically finding things,
في القرن الماضي كان الاكتشاف هوفي الأساس العثور على الأشياء
and in this century, discovery is basically making things.
وفي هذا القرن الاكتشاف هو صنع الأشياء.
De-extinction falls in that category.
واستعادة الحيوانات من الانقراض يقعضمن المجموعة الأخيرة.
So they hosted and funded this meeting. And 35 scientists,
لقد استضافوا ومولوا هذا الاجتماع.و35 عالما
they were conservation biologists and molecular biologists,
من علماء البيولوجيا الانحفاظيةوعلماء أحياء الجزيئية
basically meeting to see if they had work to do together.
التقوا أساسا لمعرفة إن كان هناك عمليمكن القيام به بشكل مشترك.
Some of these conservation biologists are pretty radical.
بعض أولئك العلماء كانوا شيئا ما جذريين.
There's three of them who are not just re-creating ancient species,
كان هناك ثلاثة منهم لا يعتبرون الأمرمجرد إعادة حيوانات قديمة للحياة
they're recreating extinct ecosystems
بل إعادة بناء نظم إيكولوجية منقرضة
in northern Siberia, in the Netherlands, and in Hawaii.
بشمال سيبيريا وهولاندا وهاواي.
Henri, from the Netherlands,
هنري من هولاندا،
with a Dutch last name I won't try to pronounce,
باسمه العائلي الهولاندي الذيسأتفادى النطق به،
is working on the aurochs.
ويعمل على الأُرْخُص.
The aurochs is the ancestor of all domestic cattle,
الأُرْخُص هو سلف كل الأبقار المستأنسة
and so basically its genome is alive, it's just unevenly distributed.
والواقع أن جيناته مازالت حيةلكنها فقط موزعة بشكل غير متساو.
So what they're doing is working with seven breeds
لدى فهم يعملون على 7 أجناس
of primitive, hardy-looking cattle like that Maremmana primitivo on the top there
بدائية وقوية من الأبقاركالمَارِيمَانَا بْرِيمِيتِيفُو بالأعلى
to rebuild, over time, with selective back-breeding,
لإعادة توليدها مع الوقت من خلال التربية الانتقائية
the aurochs.
الأُرْخُص.
Now, re-wilding is moving faster in Korea
عملية إعادة بعض المناطق للبريةفي كوريا أسرع
than it is in America,
من أمريكا،
and so the plan is, with these re-wilded areas all over Europe,
وبالنظر للمناطق التي أعيدت للبرية،فالخطة هي
they will introduce the aurochs to do its old job,
أنهم سيدخلون الأُرْخُص للقيام بعمله السابق،
its old ecological role,
دوره الإيكولوجي القديم،
of clearing the somewhat barren, closed-canopy forest
لإعادة الحياة نوعا ما للغابة الجرداءوالمظلمة
so that it has these biodiverse meadows in it.
التي ستتحول إلى مراعى خصبةومتنوعة بيولوجيا.
Another amazing story
قصة أخرى مدهشة
came from Alberto Fernández-Arias.
لأَلْبِرْتُو فِرْنَانْدِيزُ-أَرْيَاسْ.
Alberto worked with the bucardo in Spain.
كان ألبرتو يعمل على تيس البُوكَارْدُو بإسبانيا.
The last bucardo was a female named Celia
أخر بوكاردو كانت أنثى تدعى سِيلْيَا
who was still alive, but then they captured her,
التي كانت ما تزال على قيد الحياة،لكن بعد أن أمسكوا بها،
they got a little bit of tissue from her ear,
أخذوا من أذنها القليل من النسيج،
they cryopreserved it in liquid nitrogen,
ليحفظوه متجمدا في النتروجين السائل،
released her back into the wild,
ثم أطلقوها بالبرية مرة أخرى،
but a few months later, she was found dead under a fallen tree.
لكن بعد بضعة شهوروجدت ميتة تحت أنقاض شجرة.
They took the DNA from that ear,
أخذوا الحمض النووي من أذنها
they planted it as a cloned egg in a goat,
زرعوه بما يشبه البويضة المستنسخةوخصبوا به ماعز
the pregnancy came to term,
مرت فترة الحمل عادية
and a live baby bucardo was born.
ليولد بوكاردو صغير.
It was the first de-extinction in history.
كانت هذه أول عمليةاستعادة حيوان من الانقراض بالعالم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It was short-lived.
لكنها لم تستمر لفترة طويلة.
Sometimes interspecies clones have respiration problems.
فأحيانا تولد الحيونات المستنسخةبمشاكل تنفسية.
This one had a malformed lung and died after 10 minutes,
فقد ولد بعيب في شكل الرئةمات على إثره بعد 10 دقائق من ولادته،
but Alberto was confident that
لكن ألبرتو كان واثقا بأن
cloning has moved along well since then,
الاستنساخ قد أصبح أكثر تطورامنذ ذلك الوقت،
and this will move ahead, and eventually
وسيستمر في التطور، وقد يؤديفي النهاية
there will be a population of bucardos
لعودة قطيع البوكاردو
back in the mountains in northern Spain.
إلى قمم الجبال بشمال إسبانيا.
Cryopreservation pioneer of great depth is Oliver Ryder.
أُولِيفِرْ رَايْدِرْ هو واحدمن الخبراء الكبار في الحفظ بالتجميد.
At the San Diego zoo, his frozen zoo
بحديقة حيوان سان دييغو،تحتوي حديقة حيواناته المجمدة
has collected the tissues from over 1,000 species
أنسجة أزيد من 1.000 نوع جمعها
over the last 35 years.
خلال 35 سنة الأخيرة.
Now, when it's frozen that deep,
عندما تُجمد في درجات شديدة البرودة
minus 196 degrees Celsius,
أقل من 196 درجة حرارة مئوية،
the cells are intact and the DNA is intact.
يبقى الحمض النووي والخلايافي حالة سليمة.
They're basically viable cells,
وهي في مجملها خلايا في حالة جيدة،
so someone like Bob Lanza at Advanced Cell Technology
فشخص كبُوبْ لاَنْزَا،يعمل بأَدْفَنْسِدْ سِيلْ تِكْْنُولُوجِي،
took some of that tissue from an endangered animal
أخذ قليلا من نسيج حيوانمهدد بالانقراض
called the Javan banteng, put it in a cow,
هو البَانْتِنْغ أو ثور جَاوَة،حيث خصبت بقرة به
the cow went to term, and what was born
وقد مرت مرحلت الحمل ليولد
was a live, healthy baby Javan banteng,
ثور بانتنغ صغير بصحة جيدة،
who thrived and is still alive.
والذي ما يزال على قيد الحياة.
The most exciting thing for Bob Lanza
الشيء المثير في نظر بوب لانزا
is the ability now to take any kind of cell
هو أنه أصبح بالإمكان أخذأي نوع من الخلايا
with induced pluripotent stem cells
ووضعها معالخلايا الجذعية المـستحثة المتعددة القدرات
and turn it into germ cells, like sperm and eggs.
وتحويلها إلىخلية جرثومية كالمني أو البويضات.
So now we go to Mike McGrew
فلنمر إلى مَايْك مَاكْغرِيو
who is a scientist at Roslin Institute in Scotland,
وهو عالِم بمعهد روزلين باسكتلندا،
and Mike's doing miracles with birds.
ويحقق مايك معجزات مع الطيور.
So he'll take, say, falcon skin cells, fibroblast,
حيث سيأخذ، فلنقل، خلايا جلدية لصقر ماوبالتحديد خلية ليفية
turn it into induced pluripotent stem cells.
وسيحولها إلى خلاياجذعية مـستحثة متعددة القدرات
Since it's so pluripotent, it can become germ plasm.
بما أنها متعددة القدرات فإنهاقادرة على التحول إلى بلازما جرثومية.
He then has a way to put the germ plasm
ليتمكن بعدها من وضعالبلازما الجرثومية
into the embryo of a chicken egg
داخل جنين بيضة الدجاجة
so that that chicken will have, basically,
كي يمتلك ذلك الفرخ،بشكل أساسي،
the gonads of a falcon.
غدد تناسلية كالصقر.
You get a male and a female each of those,
تأخذون ديك ودجاجة
and out of them comes falcons.
ومن نسلهما تحصلون على الصقور.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Real falcons out of slightly doctored chickens.
صقور ولدت لدجاج معدل جينيا.
Ben Novak was the youngest scientist at the meeting.
كان بِنْ نُوفَاكْأصغر عالم خلال الاجتماع.
He showed how all of this can be put together.
وقد شرح لنا كيف يمكنلكل هذا أن يتكامل فيما بينه.
The sequence of events: he'll put together the genomes
في تسلسل للأحداث:يريد أن يضع كل جينات
of the band-tailed pigeon and the passenger pigeon,
الحمام ذو الذيل المخطط والحمام المهاجر،
he'll take the techniques of George Church
يود الاستعانة بتقنيات جورج تشورش
and get passenger pigeon DNA,
للحصول على الحمض النوويللحمام المهاجر،
the techniques of Robert Lanza and Michael McGrew,
وتقنيات روبرت لانزا ومايكل ماكغريو،
get that DNA into chicken gonads,
لوضع الحمض النووي بالغدد التناسليةللدجاج،
and out of the chicken gonads get passenger pigeon eggs, squabs,
ومن الغدد التناسلية للدجاجنحصل على بويضات وفراخ الحمام المهاجر،
and now you're getting a population of passenger pigeons.
لتحصلوا على سرب من الحمام المهاجر.
It does raise the question of,
لكن ذلك أثار مسألة
they're not going to have passenger pigeon parents
أن هذا الحمام المهاجرلن يكون له أبوين
to teach them how to be a passenger pigeon.
ليعلمانه كيف يعيش كحمام مهاجر.
So what do you do about that?
فماذ ستفعلون حيال ذلك؟
Well birds are pretty hard-wired, as it happens,
الحقيقة أن الطيورمبرمجة على تلك السلوكيات
so most of that is already in their DNA,
وأغلبها موجودة أصلابحمضها النووي،
but to supplement it, part of Ben's idea
واستكمالا لما سبق،كان جزء من فكرة بن
is to use homing pigeons
يتمثل باستخدام الحمام الزاجل
to help train the young passenger pigeons how to flock
لمساعدة فرخ الحمام المهاجر على تعلمكيف يطير في السرب
and how to find their way to their old nesting grounds
وكيف يعثر على طريقهإلى عشه القديم
and feeding grounds.
ومناطق التغذية.
There were some conservationists,
كان هناك بعضعلماء البيولوجيا الانحفاظية
really famous conservationists like Stanley Temple,
المشهورين مثل ستَانْلِي تِيمْبَل،
who is one of the founders of conservation biology,
الذي يعد واحد من مؤسسيعلم بيولوجيا الانحفاظية،
and Kate Jones from the IUCN, which does the Red List.
وكِيتْ جُونْز من الاتحاد الدولي لحماية الطبيعةالذي يصدر القائمة الحمراء.
They're excited about all this,
وقد تحمسوا لكل هذا الحراك العلمي،
but they're also concerned that it might be competitive
لكنهم كانوا أيضا متخوفين من أنهذا الأمر قد يتعارض
with the extremely important efforts to protect
مع الجهود الكبيرة التي بذلت لحماية
endangered species that are still alive,
الحيوانات المهددة بالانقراض
that haven't gone extinct yet.
والتي لم تنقرض بعد.
You see, you want to work on protecting the animals out there.
فكما تعلمون، يجب عليكم حمايةالحيوانات الحية بهذا العصر.
You want to work on getting the market for ivory in Asia down
عليكم العمل علىمكافحة السوق السوداء للعاج بآسيا
so you're not using 25,000 elephants a year.
التي يقتل بسببها 25.000 فيل سنويا.
But at the same time, conservation biologists are realizing
لكن في نفس الوقت بدأ يدركعلماء البيولوجيا الانحفاظية
that bad news bums people out.
بأن الأخبار السيئة تحزن الناس.
And so the Red List is really important, keep track of
ولهذا السبب فإن القائمة الحمراءجد مهمة لمعرفة
what's endangered and critically endangered, and so on.
درجات التهديد لكل حيوان.
But they're about to create what they call a Green List,
لكنهم على وشك خلقما يسمونه بالقائمة الخضراء
and the Green List will have species that are doing fine, thank you,
وهذ القائمة ستخصص للكائنات التيبدأت بالازدهار، شكرا لكم،
species that were endangered, like the bald eagle,
كالحيوانات التي كانت بخطر مثلالنسر الأصلع
but they're much better off now, thanks to everybody's good work,
لكنهم اليوم في حال أفضلوذلك بفضل العمل الرائع للجميع
and protected areas around the world
وللمحميات المنتشرة حول العالم
that are very, very well managed.
والمُسَيَّرَةِ بشكل جيد.
So basically, they're learning how to build on good news.
في الحقيقة هم يتعلمونكيفية البناء على الأخبار الجيدة.
And they see reviving extinct species
فهم يعتبرون إحياءحيوانات منقرضة من جديد
as the kind of good news you might be able to build on.
نوعا من الأخبار الجيدةالتي يمكن البناء عليها للمستقبل.
Here's a couple related examples.
هذه بعض الأمثلة.
Captive breeding will be a major part of bringing back these species.
التربية في الأسر سيكون أهم جزء في عمليةاستعادت تلك الحيوانات من الانقراض.
The California condor was down to 22 birds in 1987.
ككُنْدُورْ كاليفورنيا الذي بلغ 22 طيرا في 1987.
Everybody thought is was finished.
والكل اعتقد أن أمره قد انتهى.
Thanks to captive breeding at the San Diego Zoo,
وبفضل التربية في الأسرأصبح عددها اليوم 405 طيرا
there's 405 of them now, 226 are out in the wild.
بحديقة سان دييغو و 226 في البرية.
That technology will be used on de-extincted animals.
ونفس العملية ستستخدم في إنقاذالحيوانات من الانقراض.
Another success story is the mountain gorilla in Central Africa.
وقصة النجاح التاليةهي لغوريلا الجبل بأفريقيا الوسطى.
In 1981, Dian Fossey was sure they were going extinct.
في 1981 كانت دِيَانْ فُوسِيمتأكدة أنها ستنقرض.
There were just 254 left.
لم يبقى منها أنذاك سوى 254.
Now there are 880. They're increasing in population
اليوم يبلغ عددها 880.لقد تضاعف عددها
by three percent a year.
بنسبة 3 بالمائة.
The secret is, they have an eco-tourism program,
والسر هو اطبيقهم لبرنامجفي غاية الذكاء
which is absolutely brilliant.
وهو السياحة البيئية.
So this photograph was taken last month by Ryan
وهذه صورة التقطها ريان الشهر الماضي
with an iPhone.
بهاتفه الجوال.
That's how comfortable these wild gorillas are with visitors.
وانظروا كيف أن تلك الغوريلات مطمئنةرغم تواجدها بين زوار غرباء.
Another interesting project, though it's going to need some help,
مشروع أخر مثير للاهتمام،رغم أنه بحاجة لبعض المساعدة،
is the northern white rhinoceros.
وهو يخصوحيد القرن الأبيض الشمالي.
There's no breeding pairs left.
فليس بالأسر زوجين قادرينعلى التوالد.
But this is the kind of thing that
لكن لهكذا حالة يوجد هناك
a wide variety of DNA for this animal is available in the frozen zoo.
مجموعة متنوعة كبيرة من الحمض النوويلهذا الحيوان مجمدة.
A bit of cloning, you can get them back.
القليل من الاستنساخ،ويمكنكم بعدها استعادتهم.
So where do we go from here?
إذا مالذي سنفعله من الآن فصاعدا؟
These have been private meetings so far.
كانت هذه الاجتماعات سريةحتى الآن.
I think it's time for the subject to go public.
أعتقد أنه آن الآوان ليتحول هذا الموضوعإلى قضية رأي عام.
What do people think about it?
ما هو رأي الناس حيال هذا الأمر؟
You know, do you want extinct species back?
هل ترغبون في عودة الحيوانات المنقرضة؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Tinker Bell is going to come fluttering down.
كان هذا لوهلة جميلا وسحريا.
It is a Tinker Bell moment,
كانت هذه لحظة سحرية.
because what are people excited about with this?
ما الذي يُحَمِّس الناس لهذا الأمر؟
What are they concerned about?
ما الذي يُقْلِقُهُم بهذا الشأن؟
We're also going to push ahead with the passenger pigeon.
فنحن في طريقنا ونتقدم بشأنالحمام المهاجر.
So Ben Novak, even as we speak, is joining the group
وبينما أن أحدثكم فإن بن نوفاكيلتحق بفريق
that Beth Shapiro has at UC Santa Cruz.
بيث شابيروبجامعة كاليفورنيا بسانتا كروز.
They're going to work on the genomes
سيعملون على جينات
of the passenger pigeon and the band-tailed pigeon.
الحمام المهاجروالحمام ذو الذيل المخطط.
As that data matures, they'll send it to George Church,
وسيرسلون البيانات بانتظاملجورج تشورش
who will work his magic, get passenger pigeon DNA out of that.
الذي سيستخدم سحرهلاستخلاص الحمض النووي للحمام المهاجر.
We'll get help from Bob Lanza and Mike McGrew
وسنتلقى مساعدة منبوب لانزا ومايك ماكغريو
to get that into germ plasm that can go into chickens
لنحولها إلى بلازما جرثومية يمكن أننخصب بها الدجاج
that can produce passenger pigeon squabs
الذي سيعطينا فراخ الحمام المهاجر.
that can be raised by band-tailed pigeon parents,
والتي بدورهاسيربيها الحمام ذو الذيل المخطط
and then from then on, it's passenger pigeons all the way,
ومن تلك اللحظة لن يكون هناكسوى الحمام المهاجر
maybe for the next six million years.
وربما لستة ملايين سنة مقبلة.
You can do the same thing, as the costs come down,
وعند انخفاض تكلفة العمليةيمكن فعل نفس الشيء
for the Carolina parakeet, for the great auk,
لطيور براكيت كاروليناوالأوك العظيم
for the heath hen, for the ivory-billed woodpecker,
ودجاجة هيثونقار الخشب ذو المنقار العاجي
for the Eskimo curlew, for the Caribbean monk seal,
وكروان الإسكيمووفقمة الراهب الكاريبية
for the woolly mammoth.
والماموث الصوفي.
Because the fact is, humans have made a huge hole
لأن الحقيقة أن الإنسان تسبب في فجوة
in nature in the last 10,000 years.
بيئية ضخمة خلال 10.000 سنة الأخيرة.
We have the ability now,
لدينا القدرة اليوم
and maybe the moral obligation, to repair some of the damage.
وربما الواجب الأخلاقي، لإصلاح بعض الأضرار.
Most of that we'll do by expanding and protecting wildlands,
يمكن تحقيق معضم ذلك بزيادة وحمايةالمساحات الطبيعية
by expanding and protecting
وبزيادة أعداد وحماية
the populations of endangered species.
الحيوانات المهددة بالانقراض.
But some species
لكن بعض الأنواع
that we killed off totally
التي قضينا عليها تماما
we could consider bringing back
يمكننا استعادتها
to a world that misses them.
لعالم اشتاق لها.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Thank you.
كريس أندرسون: شكرا لك.
I've got a question.
لدي سؤال.
So, this is an emotional topic. Some people stand.
هذا موضوع عاطفي.والدليل أن بعض الناس قد وقفوا.
I suspect there are some people out there sitting,
لكني أظن أن هناك بعض الناس الجالسين هنا
kind of asking tormented questions, almost, about,
يفكرون حيال أسئلة مقلقة،من نوع،
well, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait a minute,
لحظة، لحظة، لحظة، لحظة، لحظة، لحظة،انتظروا لحظة،
there's something wrong with mankind
هناك شيء خاطئ في التدخل بهذه
interfering in nature in this way.
الطريقة في الطبيعة.
There's going to be unintended consequences.
سيؤدي ذلك لنتائج غير متوقعة.
You're going to uncork some sort of Pandora's box
ستفتحون نوعا من صندوق بَانْدُورَا
of who-knows-what. Do they have a point?
لا أحد يعلم ما قد يخرج منه.هل هم على صواب فيما يفعلون؟
Stewart Brand: Well, the earlier point is
سْتِيوَارْت بْرَانْد: النقطة الأولى هي،
we interfered in a big way by making these animals go extinct,
أننا قد تدخلنا بشكل كبيروجعلنا هذه الحيوانات تنقرض
and many of them were keystone species,
والعديد منها كانت أنواع جد مهمة
and we changed the whole ecosystem they were in
وقد غيرنا كل النظام البيئيالذي عاشت فيه
by letting them go.
بجعلها تختفي.
Now, there's the shifting baseline problem, which is,
الآن هناك مشكل أساسي صغير
so when these things come back,
وهو أنه عند عودة هذه الكائنات
they might replace some birds that are there
قد تعود بعض الطيور الموجودة
that people really know and love.
والتي يعرفها الناس جيدا ويحبونها.
I think that's, you know, part of how it'll work.
أعتقد أن هذا كما تعرفون جزءامن كيفية عمل هذه العملية.
This is a long, slow process --
فهذه عملية طويلة الأمد وبطيئة --
One of the things I like about it, it's multi-generation.
من الأشياء التي أحبها في هذا الأمرأنه يمكن توريثه جيلا بعد جيل.
We will get woolly mammoths back.
سوف نقوم بإعادة الماموث الصوفي.
CA: Well it feels like both the conversation
ك أ: يبدو أن الحديث
and the potential here are pretty thrilling.
والإمكانيات المتعلقة بهذا الأمر جد مثيرة.
Thank you so much for presenting. SB: Thank you.
شكرا جزيلا على العرض.- س ب: شكرا لكم.
CA: Thank you. (Applause)
ك أ: شكرا لكم.(تصفيق)